<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Hrishikesh</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2021, Hrishikesh Terdalkar.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hube9c3e5f7a27217c9c8565129307f591_12218_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Annotation for Knowledge Graphs</title>
      <link>/project/annotation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/annotation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sangrahaka&lt;/em&gt; is a web-based tool for annotating entities and
relationships from text corpora towards construction of a knowledge graph
and subsequent querying using templatized natural language questions.  The
application is language and corpus agnostic, but can be tuned for specific
needs of a language or a corpus.  The application is freely available for
download and installation.  Besides having a user-friendly interface, it is
fast, supports customization, and is fault tolerant on both client and
server side.  It outperforms other annotation tools in an objective
evaluation metric.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sanskrit Question Answering</title>
      <link>/project/sanskrit/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/sanskrit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sanskrit (&lt;em&gt;Saṃskṛta&lt;/em&gt;) enjoys one of the largest and most varied literature in the whole world. Extracting the knowledge from it, however, is a challenging task due to multiple reasons including complexity of the language and paucity of standard natural language processing tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, we target the problem of building general purpose knowledge graphs (KG) from Sanskrit texts as well as building natural language question answering systems on top of the constructed KGs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
