<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Hrishikesh Terdalkar</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 09:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hube9c3e5f7a27217c9c8565129307f591_12218_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chandojñānam</title>
      <link>/project/chandojnana/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 09:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/chandojnana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Majority of the Sanskrit literature is in the form of poetry that adheres to the
rules of Sanskrit prosody or Chandaḥśāstra, which is the study of Sanskrit
meters, known as chandas. The purpose of chanda is primarily to add rhythm to
the text so that it is easier to memorize. Additionally, it also helps in
preserving the correctness to some extent. Chandojñānam is a web-based Sankrit
prosodical meter identification and utilization system. In addition to the core
functionality of identifying meters from Sanskrit text, it provides fuzzy (i.e.,
approximate and close) matches for text that does not correspond exactly to a
known metrical pattern. This opens up the scope of a meter based correction of
erroneous digital corpora. The system supports identification of meters from
uploaded images by using optical character recognition (OCR) engines in the
backend. It is also able to process entire text files at a time. The text can be
processed in two modes, either by treating it as a list of individual lines, or
as a collection of verses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PyCDSL</title>
      <link>/project/pycdsl/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/pycdsl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;PyCDSL is a python interface to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sanskrit-lexicon.uni-koeln.de/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cologne Digital Sanskrit Lexicon (CDSL)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free software: GNU General Public License v3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Documentation: &lt;a href=&#34;https://pycdsl.readthedocs.io&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://pycdsl.readthedocs.io&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CDSL Corpus Management (Download, Update, Access)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unified interface to access all dictionaries available at CDSL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Console command and REPL interface for easy dictionary search&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extensive support for transliteration using &lt;code&gt;indic-transliteration&lt;/code&gt; module&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;usage&#34;&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PyCDSL can be used in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://pycdsl.readthedocs.io/en/latest/usage.html#using-pycdsl-in-a-project&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;python project&lt;/a&gt;, as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://pycdsl.readthedocs.io/en/latest/usage.html#using-console-interface-of-pycdsl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;console command&lt;/a&gt; and as an &lt;a href=&#34;https://pycdsl.readthedocs.io/en/latest/usage.html#using-repl-interface-of-pycdsl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;interactive REPL interface&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jñānasaṅgrahaḥ</title>
      <link>/project/jnanasangraha/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2020 09:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/jnanasangraha/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Question-Answering System for Ramayana</title>
      <link>/project/iks-aicte-ramayana-question-answering/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/iks-aicte-ramayana-question-answering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sanskrit is one of the most ancient and richest languages in the world. Its
literature boasts of text spanning every facet of life and contains works on
mathematics, arts, sciences, religion, philosophy, etc. Unfortunately, the large
volume of such works and the relative lack of proficiency in the language have
kept treasures in those text hidden from the common man. Unraveling information
from these texts in a targeted and systematic manner can not only help in
enhancing the knowledge systems but can also revive an interest in the language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sanskrit enjoys one of the largest and most varied literature in the whole
world. Extracting the knowledge from it, however, is a challenging task due to
multiple reasons including complexity of the language and paucity of standard
natural language processing tools. Therefore, we explore the construction of
knowledge graphs through the process of manual annotation of a Sanskrit text,
Vālmīki Rāmāyaṇa. We have developed a comprehensive NLP annotation tool,
Antarlekhaka, which is being used for this large scale annotation task.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
