<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>question answering | Hrishikesh Terdalkar</title>
    <link>/tag/question-answering/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/question-answering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>question answering</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023, Hrishikesh Terdalkar.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hube9c3e5f7a27217c9c8565129307f591_12218_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>question answering</title>
      <link>/tag/question-answering/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Framework for Question-Answering in Sanskrit through Automated Construction of Knowledge Graphs</title>
      <link>/publication/iscls2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/iscls2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- Supplementary notes can be added here, including [code, math, and images](https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/). --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Question-Answering System for Ramayana</title>
      <link>/project/iks-aicte-ramayana-question-answering/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/iks-aicte-ramayana-question-answering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sanskrit is one of the most ancient and richest languages in the world. Its
literature boasts of text spanning every facet of life and contains works on
mathematics, arts, sciences, religion, philosophy, etc. Unfortunately, the large
volume of such works and the relative lack of proficiency in the language have
kept treasures in those text hidden from the common man. Unraveling information
from these texts in a targeted and systematic manner can not only help in
enhancing the knowledge systems but can also revive an interest in the language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sanskrit enjoys one of the largest and most varied literature in the whole
world. Extracting the knowledge from it, however, is a challenging task due to
multiple reasons including complexity of the language and paucity of standard
natural language processing tools. Therefore, we explore the construction of
knowledge graphs through the process of manual annotation of a Sanskrit text,
Vālmīki Rāmāyaṇa. We have developed a comprehensive NLP annotation tool,
Antarlekhaka, which is being used for this large scale annotation task.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
